"The TAME Trial—
Targeting Aging with Metformin"
Given the evidence
that diabetics
taking the drug metformin
may live longer
than people who
don't even have diabetes
suggests metformin
has an anti-aging effect,
slowing the diseases of aging
and, in doing so,
extending both
health and lifespans,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
There are a few small,
brief trials of metformin
on healthy volunteers,
for example,
randomizing
a dozen or so individuals
to metformin
or placebo for a few weeks,
comparing the effects
on muscle and fat biopsies.
Beneficial changes
in gene expression
in various
aging pathways were noted,
along with objective
improvements in risk factors,
such as LDL cholesterol
and triglycerides,
but what we'd really like
are hard endpoints,
like disease outcomes and death.
Enter the TAME trial,
Targeting Aging with Metformin.
Spearheaded by the nonprofit
American Federation
for Aging Research,
TAME has the ambitious goal
of randomizing 3,000
nondiabetic individuals
aged 65-79
to metformin or placebo
over a period of six years
to assess the effect
on age-related conditions,
such as heart attacks,
stroke,
cancer,
dementia,
and death.
Current treatments
"just exchange one disease
for another," railed
the principal investigator.
Someone cured of cancer
may just drop dead the next year
from a heart attack.
"What we want to show
is that if we delay aging,
that's the best way
to delay disease."
Sadly,
though the TAME trial
received FDA approval in 2015,
it has yet
to get off the ground.
You can guess why.
As the editor-in-chief
of an anti-aging journal put it,
"There is no way in hell
to make money out of it."
Metformin's patent
expired decades ago,
and generics retail
at pennies a pill.
It's considered
a "genuinely good use
of 75 million dollars,"
but the researchers
have only evidently
been able to raise $11 million
from private donors.
Some in Silicon Valley
tech circles
aren't waiting for the results.
Apparently, some techies
have started taking metformin
in a bid to live longer,
though it's only officially
available by prescription
for diabetes.
Metformin is cheap,
relatively safe,
and one of the most
promising drugs to combat
age-related diseases,
but there are reasons
to temper our expectations.
Though it's been referred
to as a "magic drug,"
the longevity benefits in mice
were small and dose dependent.
At best, it may increase
the average lifespan
of certain mice by five percent,
but at a higher dose,
actually shortens lifespan.
Much of the enthusiasm
for the TAME trial
rests on it acting
as a test case
to successfully get regulatory
authorities, like the FDA,
to formally recognize
any treatment
for the aging process itself,
in hopes that this will
arouse Big Pharma
to invest large-scale R&D
to advance the field.
Further reservations
about the panacean prospects
placed on metformin
arise from the landmark
Diabetes
Prevention Program study
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine.
Thousands of prediabetic
individuals were randomized
to metformin
or placebo for years
to see if the drug
could prevent their prediabetes
from turning
into full-blown diabetes.
It worked,
reducing overall
diabetes incidence by 31 percent
compared to placebo,
but it didn't for everyone.
For example, it didn't appear
to significantly benefit
those 60 years or older
and only seemed
to help those most at risk--
those with class II obesity
and the highest blood sugars.
Those with lower
(but still elevated)
blood sugars,
and those under a BMI of 35
did not have their diabetes risk
significantly dampened
by the drug.
One small study even found that,
while metformin alleviated
the insulin resistance
of diabetics
and those with
a family history of diabetes,
metformin actually worsened
the insulin resistance
(the cause of prediabetes
and type 2 diabetes)
of nondiabetic obese individuals
that didn't have
a genetic predisposition.
If you have diabetes,
it can make things better;
if you don't,
it may make things worse.
So, healthier individuals
may not reap the benefits
of metformin
that some try to extrapolate
from those
longevity studies on diabetics.
In fact, even those researchers
are explicit that
they don't think metformin
is ready for prime time
as an anti-aging intervention
by the general population.
What's safer
and works even better?
There was a third arm
of the Diabetes Prevention
Program study.
Thousands of prediabetics
were randomized
to metformin or placebo
or lifestyle changes--
a cholesterol-lowering
low-fat diet and exercise,
at least about 20 minutes a day
moderate intensity exercise,
such as brisk walking.
Compared to the placebo group,
those taking metformin
were 31 percent less likely
to develop diabetes.
The lifestyle group
was 58 percent less likely.
Making simple lifestyle changes
was nearly
twice as effective as metformin
(and with fewer side effects--
for example,
six times fewer cases
of gastrointestinal distress).
Other randomized
controlled trials
have found the same thing--
lifestyle approaches superior
to drug-based approaches
for diabetes prevention.
And, that 60 or so percent
drop in risk was not among those
who actually made
the lifestyle change,
just those instructed to do so.
Another diabetes
prevention trial
published in the New England
Journal of Medicine
that found the same
58 percent reduction
in diabetes risk
among those asked
to make lifestyle changes
drilled down to see
what the benefit was
for those who fully complied.
Only a fraction
of the lifestyle
intervention group
met the modest goals.
Only about a third
increased their exercise,
for example.
Only about a quarter
met the minimum
recommended intake of fiber
(found concentrated
in whole plant foods)
or cut down
on enough saturated fat
(mostly dairy, dessert,
chicken, and pork).
But, they did better
than the control group,
and fewer of them developed
diabetes because of it.
But, what if you look
just at the folks
who actually made all
(or even just 4 out of 5)
of the recommended
lifestyle changes?
They had zero diabetes--
none of them got diabetes
over the course of the study,
meaning effectively
a 100 percent drop in risk.